# Diego Alburez-Gutierrez

Konrad-Zuse-Straße 1, 18057 Rostock, Germany

Email: alburezgutierrez@demogr.mpg.de Web: www.alburez.me; Twitter: @d\_alburez

I am a social scientist specialising in inter-generational demography. My work has used mathematical modeling, micro-simulation techniques, and empirical analysis to explore changes in the experience of life events such as kin availability, family bereavement, and caring responsibilities across demographic regimes.

#### **EDUCATION**

## The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

PhD, Demography and Population Studies

2014 - 2018

- Title: "Beyond excess mortality: the demographic life of a Mayan community after a war of massacres"
- Primary data collection: genealogical surveys and in-depth interviews (1 year fieldwork)
- Supervisors: Arjan Gjonça, Tiziana Leone, Ernestina Coast, and Michael Murphy

MSc, Social Research Methods (Distinction)

2013-2014

Practical approach with emphasis on quantitative and qualitative data analysis

# Del Valle University, Guatemala

BA, Anthropology (First class/Summa Cum Laude)

2008-2012

## AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

- Poster award (2021), Population Association of America Annual Meeting. Poster title: "Linking excess mortality to Google mobility data during the COVID-19 pandemic in England and Wales." (Basellini, U., Alburez-Gutierrez, D., Del Fava, E., Perrotta, D., Bonetti, M., Camarda, C. and Zagheni, E.).
- Otto Hahn Medal (2019) awarded by the Max Planck Society for 'outstanding achievement from the initial creative period of young scientists'
- LSE PhD Academy Prize (2018) awarded by the London School of Economics for research on state-sponsored massacres in Guatemala
- LSE PhD Studentship (2014-2018) awarded by the London School of Economics

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Germany

Research Scientist (post-doc), Lab of Digital and Computational Demography

Jan 2019 - present

Research Area Chair, Lab of Digital and Computational Demography Sep 2019 - Sep 2021 Research-administrative role leading a group of four researchers in the 'Aging and Generational Processes' Research Area.

# United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR), Denmark

Statistics Team Intern, Field Information and Coordination Support Section (FICSS) Mar - Jun 2018 Central role in implementing UNHCR's Demographic Projection Tool.

# The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

Research Assistant, Law Department

Apr - Jul 2017

Leading qualitative research on low student satisfaction

Research Assistant, Social Policy Department

Mar 2016- Jun 2017

Quantitative analysis of maternal and child health outcomes in Palestine

Research Assistant, Sociology Department

Sep 2014 - Sep 2015

Qualitative coding and analysis of methodological practices in sociology of work

Research Assistant, Methodology Department

Oct 2013 - Jan 2014

Survey of grey literature to identify common qualitative methods in International Development

## Public Opinion Program, Universidad Rafael Landívar, Guatemala

Lead researcher

Jul - Nov 2013

Designing and implementing qualitative research for the Media Monitoring Project

## The Population Council, Guatemala

Research Sub Coordinator

Jan - Dec 2012

- Design and implementation of qualitative research on conditional cash transfer programmes
- Led team of four ethnographers during six months of data collection in rural Guatemala

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# International Max Planck Research School for Population, Health and Data Science (IMPRS-PHDS)

Class Teacher for course "Topics in Digital and Computational Demography"

2020 - present

## European Doctoral School of Demography (EDSD), Barcelona

Class Teacher for course "Digital Demography"

2020 - present

# The London School of Economics and Political Science, UK

Class Teacher, Social Policy Department

2016-2017

- Leading seminars for the course "Introduction to Global Population Change"
- Weekly office hours, updated course website, homework and exam marking

Class Teacher, LSE Methods Summer School

2015

- Leading seminars for the "Qualitative Research Methods" strand
- Homework and exam marking

#### Del Valle University, Guatemala

Class teacher, Anthropology and Sociology Department

2013

- Leading seminars for the course "Advanced qualitative data analysis"
- Course design, homework and exam marking

Class teacher, Anthropology and Sociology Department Leading seminars for the course "History of Anthropology 1" 2011

#### PUBLICATIONS IN PEER-REVIEWED JOURNALS

(conventionally, the first author is the main author in demographic publications)

- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Mason, C., and Zagheni, E. (2021). "The 'Sandwich Generation' Revisited: Global Demographic Drivers of Care Time Demands." *Population and Development Review*. Advanced Publication. doi: 10.1111/padr.12436.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Kolk, M., and Zagheni, E. (2021) "Women's experience of child death: A global demographic perspective." *Demography*. Advanced Publication. doi: 10.1215/00703370-9420770.
- Smith-Greenaway, E., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, Trinitapoli, J, and Zagheni, E. (2021) "The Global Burden of Maternal Bereavement: Indicators of the Cumulative Prevalence of Child Loss." *BMJ Global Health*, 6:e004837. doi: bmjgh-2020-004837
- Martinez-Folgar, K., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Paniagua-Avila, A., Ramirez-Zea, M., Bilal, U. (2021). "Excess Mortality during the COVID-19 Pandemic in Guatemala". *American Journal of Public Health*. Advanced Publication.
- Basellini, U., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Del Fava, E., Perrotta, D., Bonetti, M., Camarda, C. and Zagheni, E. (2021). "Linking excess mortality to Google mobility data during the COVID-19 pandemic in England and Wales." SSM Population Health, 14. doi: j.ssmph.2021.100799.
- Riffe, T., Acosta E., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, the COVerAGE-DB team. (2021) "Data Resource Profile: COVerAGE-DB: a global demographic database of COVID-19 cases and deaths." *International Journal of Epidemiology*, 50(2): 390-390f. doi: 10.1093/ije/dyab027.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D**. (2021). Vivir para contarla: un análisis demográfico de las masacres de Río Negro en Guatemala (1980-1982) [Living to tell the tale: A demographic analysis of the Rio Negro massacres in Guatemala (1980-1982)]. *Análisis de la Realidad Nacional*, 208:91–104. ISSN:2227-9113.
- Nepomuceno, M., Acosta, E., **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Aburto, J.M., Gagnon, A., and Turra, C. (2020). "Besides population age-structure, health and other demographic factors can contribute to understanding the COVID-19 burden." *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences*, 117(25). doi:10.1073/pnas.2008760117.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D**. (2019). Blood is thicker than bloodshed: A genealogical approach to reconstruct populations after armed conflicts. *Demographic Research*, 40(23): 627-656. doi:10.4054/DemRes.2019.40.23.
- Leone, T., Alburez-Gutierrez, D., Gandour, R., Coast, E., and Giacaman, R. (2019). "Maternal and child access to care and intensity of conflict in the occupied Palestinian territory: a pseudo-longitudinal analysis (2000–2014)." Conflict and Health 13(36). doi:10.1186/s13031-019-0220-2.
- McGovern, P., and **D. Alburez-Gutierrez**. (2017) "Who takes workplace case-study methods seriously? The influence of gender, academic rank and PhD training." *Industrial Relations Journal* 48(2):98-114, doi:10.1111/irj.12171.

Alburez-Gutierrez, D., S. Aref, S. Gil-Clavel, A. Grow, D.V. Negraia, E. Zagheni. (2019). "Demography in the Digital Era: New Data Sources for Population Research." *Proceedings of the 2019 Conference of the Italian Statistical Society.* doi: 10.31235/osf.io/24jp7.

## TECHNICAL REPORTS

**Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** and Segura Garcia, C. (2018). "The UNHCR Demographic Projection Tool: estimating the future size and composition of forcibly displaced populations." *UNHCR Statistics Technical Series*: 2018/1. Copenhagen: United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees.

#### WORKING PAPERS AND PAPERS IN PROGRESS

- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.** (unpublished). "The demographic drivers of grief and memory after genocide in Guatemala." Submitted to *Demography* (revise and resubmit) doi:10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2021-003.
- Williams, I. and **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (2021). "Mortality change and its impact on child survival." MPIDR Working Paper. Rostock: Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research. doi:10.4054/MPIDR-WP-2021-001.
- Castro, A. and **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (2021). "North and South: Naming practices and the hidden dimension of global disparities in knowledge production." MPIDR Working Paper. Rostock: Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research. doi:MPIDR-WP-2021-014.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Barban, N., Caswell, H., Kolk, M., Margolis, R., Smith-Greenaway, E., Song, X., Verdery, A., and Zagheni, E. (unpublished). "Kinship Approaches in Demography: Review and Key Areas for Future Development." Manuscript submitted to the 2022 Annual Conference of the Population Association of America.
- **Alburez-Gutierrez, D.**, Basellini, U., and Zagheni, E. (unpublished) "When do mothers bury a child? 'Untimely' offspring loss and the demographic transition." Manuscript submitted to the 2022 Annual Conference of the Population Association of America.
- Snyder, M, Alburez-Gutierrez, D., Williams, I., and Zagheni, E. (2021). "The Lived Experience of COVID-19 Mortality: Quantifying the Relationship between Excess Mortality and Family Bereavement." Manuscript submitted to the 2022 Annual Conference of the Population Association of America.

## SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT

- Williams, I. and **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.** (2021). "DemoKin: An R package to implement matrix kinship models in stable and non-stable populations." https://github.com/IvanWilli/DemoKin.
- Theile, T., **Alburez-Gutierrez**, **D.**, et al. (unpublished). "RSocsim: A multi-platform R package to run and analyse demographic microsimulations using SOCSIM."

# INVITED TALKS (SELECTED)

- "The Demographic Drivers of Grief and Memory After Genocide in Guatemala." UW Seminar Series. Seattle, USA (University of Washington, 20 April 2021, online due to Covid-19).
- "Linking excess mortality to Google mobility data during the COVID-19 pandemic." Mexico City, Mexico (El Colegio de Mexico, 16 April 2021, online due to Covid-19).

- "The 'Sandwich Generation' Revisited: Global Demographic Drivers of Care Time Demands." Population and Health Research Group Seminar Series, St Andrews, Scotland (University of St Andrews, 08 Dec 2020, online due to Covid-19).
- "Women's experience of child death: a global demographic perspective." ISER External Seminar, Colchester, UK (Institute for Social and Economic Research, University of Essex, 27 November 2019).
- "The Demographic Foundations of the Lived Experience of Kin Death: A Genealogical Reconstruction." SUDA Demographic Colloquium Series, Stockholm, Sweden (Stockholm University, 23 May 2019).
- "Ciencias Sociales Computacionales: Retos y oportunidades en la era digital [Computational Social Sciences: challenges and opportunities in the Digital Age]". Guatemala City, Guatemala (Latin American Faculty of Social Sciences, 25 April 2019).
- "Mass killings, family support, and survival: evidence from Guatemala." SUDA Demographic Colloquium Series, Stockholm, Sweden (Stockholm University, 8 February 2018).

#### OUTREACH AND SCIENCE COMMUNICATION

- News magazine of the International Union for the Scientific Study of Population: "Global trends of offspring loss: towards a more equitable future?" (N-IUSSP, Sep 2021.)
- Podcast episode: "Demografía y la experiencia de muerte [Demography and the experience of death]" (Divulga Podcast, episode 31, May 2021)
- Academic video: "How Can We Quantify the Immediate and Lingering Impact of Genocide on Local Populations?" (Latest Thinking, Apr 2020)
- Opinion piece: "Coronavirus: a warning to Latin America and the Caribbean to dramatically increase COVID-19 testing" (The Conversation, UK, Apr 2020)
- Blog post: "Genocide is the tip of the iceberg: Reviewing the Guatemalan case" (LSE Human Rights Blog, Feb 2016)

## ORGANISER OF INTERNATIONAL ACADEMIC EVENTS

- Coordinator of the Seminar Series of the Lab of Digital and Computational Demography, Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research. 2020-2021
- Organiser and moderator: Panel Discussion on Digital and Computational Demography, IX Conference of the Latin American Association for Population Studies, Santiago, Chile (online) 2020
- Organiser: Rostock Open Science Workshop, Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Rostock
- Organiser: Workshop on Demographic Research with Web and Social Media Data, 13<sup>th</sup> International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM), Munich 2019

## SERVICE TO THE DISCIPLINE

• Reviewer for academic journals: Demography; Population and Development Review; Population Studies; European Journal of Population; Journal of Marriage and Family; Demographic Research; Revue Quetelet/Quetelet Journal; BMC Public Health; PLOS ONE; Scientific Reports; EPJ Data Science; International Conference on Social Informatics (SocInfo)

- Organiser of the 'Social Policy Qualitative Research Group', London School of Economics 2017-2018
- President of the 'Methodology Student Union', London School of Economics 2013-2014
- President of the 'Social Sciences Student Union', Del Valle University (Guatemala) 2011-2012

# PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

- International Union for the Scientific Study of Population (IUSSP)
- British Society for Population Studies (BSPS)
- Population Association of America (PAA)
- European Association for Population Studies (EAPS)
- Latin American Association for Population Studies (ALAP)
- Latin American Studies Association (LASA)
- Households in Conflict Network (HiCN)
- Population Health and Armed Conflict Network (PHAAC)
- International Science, Technology, and Innovation Network of Guatemala (REDCTI)

## **SKILLS**

- Statistical programming: R (base, tidyverse, data.table, parallel, shiny), Stata, Excel
- Text processing and web: LATEX, MS Office, (r)markdown, HTML, JavaScript, Tesseract
- Other programming: Git, Python 3, SQL, Hadoop
- Demographic microsimulation: SOCSIM with applications in R
- Qualitative data analysis: NVivo, Atlas.ti
- Experience in qualitative, quantitative, and online data collection

### LANGUAGES

- International: **Spanish** (native), **English** (full professional C2), **German** (full professional C1), **Swedish** (beginner A1)
- Guatemalan: K'iche' (full professional C1), Achi (full professional C1), Kaqchikel (professional B1), Q'eqchi' (limited working A2)